Gabor Peterdi Papers
Gabor Peterdi Papers
1939-1969
Peterdi, Gabor.
l.75 linear ft.
Papers of the American painter, printmaker. Born 1915 in Hungary. Writings, including articles, essays, and book manuscripts for Great prints of the world, and: Printmaking: methods old and new; reproductions of artwork; and printed material, including articles and clippings about Peterdi (1955-1968), an extensive assortment of exhibition catalogs for one-man and group shows (1939-1969), and periodical reviews.
149477
Biographical History
Gabor Peterdi was a Hungarian-born American painter and graphic artist.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1939 to 1969, the Gabor Peterdi Papers comprises reproductions of artwork, writings and memorabilia of the Hungarian-born American painter and graphic artist (b. 1915). With the exception of two typescript book manuscripts, the entire collection consists of printed material which documents Peterdi's professional career.
Artwork consists of reproductions of Peterdi's works.
Writings include published articles and essays, typescripts for Peterdi's Great Prints of the World and Printmaking: Methods Old and New, and miscellaneous printed comments by Peterdi on his work.
Memorabilia includes articles about Peterdi (1955-1968), an extensive collection of exhibition catalogs and announcements for his one-man (1959-1968) and group shows (1939-1969), periodical reviews (1956-1966), and an assortment of brochures, flyers, reports, and miscellaneous printed material in which the artist is mentioned.
Arrangement of the Collection
Writings are arranged alphabetically by type and then title. Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Peterdi, Gabor Archives.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Hungarian Americans.; Painters, United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Printmakers, United States.; Prints, 20th century, United States.; Prints, Technique.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Essays.; Exhibition catalogs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Reviews (documents); Artists.; Painters.; Printmakers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Artwork
  - Reproductions, 1959-1967; undated (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Articles, essays
    - "An Artist's Approach to Drawing" - publication of text of a lecture delivered at the Metropolitan Museum of Art - Approaches to Drawing - The Drawing Society, 1963 (Box 1)
    - "A Biography of My Landscape" - Art in America, no. 3, 1963 (Box 1)
    - "Education and the Artist in the United States" - contribution to Profile: Art and Artists in the U.S.A. - published on the occasion of the Fourth Congress of the International Association of Plastic Arts, 1963 (Box 1)
    - "Experiments in Contemporary Intaglio Printmaking" - Art Education, Apr. 1964 (Box 1)
    - "Humanism and Hucksterism in Contemporary Art" - Yale Literary Magazine, Mar. 1962 (Box 1)
    - "The Renaissance of Contemporary Graphic Arts" - The League, Fall 1951 (Box 1)
  - Books
    - Great Prints of the World - typescript ms., 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Printmaking: Methods Old and New - typescript ms., copy-edited, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellany, 1954; 1958,; undated (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Articles about, 1955-1968; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Brochures, flyers, reports, etc. in which Peterdi is mentioned, 1961-1967; undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1963-1967; undated (Box 2)
  - Exhibition catalogs, announcements
    - One-man shows, 1959-1968; undated; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Group shows, 1939-1954; 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Group shows, 1955-1969; 12 folders (Box 3)
    - Group shows, undated; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Reviews, 1956-1966 (Box 4)